Someone who crosses the sea?
on a speed boat to Spain,?
running away from poverty,?
is exposed to anything.?
There were ten of us on the boat.?
We were four days at sea.?
I was very nervous?
and feared for our lives.?
Sea rescue team, we have
the position of a boat.
-South to southwest. 35 50.
-Roger that. Thanks.
The motor worked, but?
there wasn't enough gas to get to Spain.?
The wind was blowing against us?
and pushed in the opposite direction?
and we ran out of bottles?
of gasoline.?
When we stopped,?
we had no clue where we were,?
if in Spain or not.?
I only thought about dying.?
Continue searching, starting
with the island of Alborán.
I thought I wouldn't get out alive.?
Four days of hunger and thirst.?
I could see death before me.?
We saw a chance to survive?
when we saw the patrol ship.?
-What's their position?
-They are not moving.
It's a pneumatic boat,
about six or seven metres.
First, a small plane arrived,?
keeping its distance from us.?
It flew watching over us.?
Then came the police helicopter.?
It was still and taking photos.?
Then came a boat to save us.?
Sea rescue team, do you have
a visual of the boat?
-There it is.
-Right at the bow.
I left Morocco?
to have a future.?
I want my own family,?
to have kids,?
open a barber shop,?
have a house, like anyone else.?
God saved us.?
C'mon! C'mon!
C'mon! Let's go!
It's alright!
Europe is considered
the land of hope and light,
where everything is easy
and nothing is impossible.
Many still see it that way,
despite everything they say
in the news about the crisis.
People don't believe it.
I'm another victim of life.
Because of my parents
or whoever,
I was born in Morocco and now
I suffer the consequences.
I wanted a new reality.
I thought it was unfair
and the power to change
was in my own hands.
When I was 10, I thought
about my future:
I quit school
and started working,
which makes you
grow up very fast.
You earn five euro,
which is almost
50 dirhams for a week,
which gets you nowhere.
One day I said "Enough.
I need to leave this place".
They come from Maghreb
or Sub-Saharan Africa,
are minors and travel alone
risking their lives in the dessert,
on a speed boat,
or hidden in a truck.
If they are lucky,
they'll reach the promise land
and live in juvenile centres,
until they reach legal age.
That day, on their 18th birthday,
they say goodbye,
more alone and vulnerable
than when they arrived.
18 YEARS AND A DAY
On their birthday,
in most of the cases,
they are left in the streets.
They are left forced
to live like adults
without any resources
and, in most cases,
without a place to live
arranged beforehand.
Most end up calling
the Social Services
to get a place to sleep
in any of the homeless centres
in the different
autonomous regions.
My name is Redouane,
I was born in Tetouan
on the 12 of January of 2000.
When I was in the youth centre,
I was turning 18 soon.
They don't help you
if you are about to turn 18.
They don't do anything.
On my birthday,
they told me I had to go.
I know I had to leave,
but I need help.
I have no family here.
They tell you to leave
or they'll call Social Services.
I told them to call, because
I don't have where to sleep.
Most of the time
they see the case as...
There's the door.
Go figure it out.
The social services
of Samur Social
in Madrid tell us
that we can't take someone
who just turned 18
and slept the night before
in a youth centre,
because it's not
a case of emergency.
It should be anticipated.
Appropriate accommodation
should be foreseen.
On my birthday,
I slept in a garage.
A garage with drunk people.
I didn't have a bed,
but a hard chair.
That's where we slept.
The dreams I had in Morocco
didn't come true
when I arrived here.
Life is difficult.
In the Raíces Foundation,
which works
for young people's rights,
we meet Ayoub.
He needs help, as the police
have given him a deportation order.
What's worse than turning 18
and being on the street
is leaving the centre
without a legalised status.
They wouldn't help me.?
For the five months?
I was there,?
all they said were lies.?
I would ask the Director?
if they processed my application?
and only gave excuses.?
She would tell me?
they'd do it next week?
and the same thing?
until I turned 18.?
Then, they told me?
I had to leave.?
Ayoub spent five months
in this centre in Viznar, Granada,
opened in 2017
as an emergency centre
to accommodate huge
amounts of young foreigners.
They gave him a roof,
food, and a bed,
but threw him to the streets
without a residence permit,
making him an adult
with an illegal status.
Of course, without a tutor
they won't process
the residence permit
and, in most cases,
there won't even be
a process for documentation,
they won't contact
the due embassy or consulate
to get the official
documentation of the children,
leaving them in
an illegal situation
caused by
the Spanish administration.
According to state data,
within the first nine months
of 2018, in Spain, there were
almost 5,000 immigrant children
and residence permits
were being processed
for only 8% of them.
More than have of them
come into Spain
through the southern coast.
I admit that sometimes
it's impossible to get it,
especially if the minor
turns 18 in three months.
We can't help much.
Luckily, and I speak
in the case of Málaga,
those cases are
very few.
In our case,
we have levels of priority
for those who are about
to reach legal age,
and we can't wait,
so we can go ahead
and file a case of homelessness.
But, if they come in
short months away from 18
and the due consulate
doesn't help,
it's very hard.
Málaga is not only
packed with young immigrants
that leave youth centres
under the provincial care.
They come from all over Andalusia
and, in some cases,
from Ceuta and Melilla,
as they know the city
holds a facility
to host homeless people,
created by the Town Hall
and 10 social entities.
It's called Puerta Única
and has a specific protocol
for such youngsters.
Five years ago we identify
a new profile of youngsters
between 18 and 20
that invade housing
in the city centre.
When the police finds them,
we see that
they are usually Moroccan,
very young, that's true,
without schooling,
without any form
of legal papers,
and, mostly, without speaking Spanish.
We start working with them
and learn they were
released from centres
or other youth units
of the government of Andalusia,
but no one informed us.
Andalusia gives them,
literally, 20 euro
and when they turn 18
they let them out the centre
without any type of
care system.
These kids,
more than vulnerable,
are in the lowest level
of social exclusion.
When you are illegal,
don't speak the language,
don't have any money
or any education,
don't have where to sleep,
it's the lowest level
of social exclusion.
I arrived to Melilla
and was living on the street.
I know people
who sleep here,
homeless people
that sleep here.
A boy who leaves the centre
and turns 18 years old,
without documentation or anything.
People who come on a boat
from Melilla, Ceuta, or Morocco
come here to sleep.
There are two mattresses
and a roof on top.
I found the bed
in the rubbish and brought it here,
making myself a hut.
This is the roof,
with wood and cardboard.
The plastic stops the rain
so it doesn't get wet.
In summer you don't need
the plastic cover,
but in winter, the rain
and the cold gets in.
Abdelali is a young man
who was in Melilla,
where he turned 18
and, he was released
without documentation
due to administration problems,
making him live on the street
for 10 more months,
until he was able
to get his permit.
Given that its retroactive,
when he acquired
his residence permit,
he only had two months
to renew the permit.
That's when he goes to Málaga
entering the system
for homeless people.
First and foremost,
they must find a place
in the local shelter
of San Juan de Dios
or the apartments
Puerta Única has
to keep them away
from the streets and danger.
Drugs are a big danger,
as can be prostitution.
It's easy to think
they don't fit in or adjust,
but you see it differently
from their perspective.
Integration is not easy.
Without the right tools,
it's not easy.
They can't do it alone.
The system is vital,
and the system doesn't protect them.
The system has isolated them.
The new guys
usually sleep under bridges
here in Málaga
or squatting houses,
while in summer
they stay near the beach.
Puerta Única has
a mobile unit
that goes around the city
365 days a year
to offer homeless people
the resources of the unit
in Málaga.
Exceptionally, Nordin
takes us around
to see if there are
young immigrants in the street.
Many times,
we can find, in this case,
boys sleeping in the street,
an we invade their space.
It's key to respect them
and to ask for permission:
to sit down with them,
boy or girl...
These are key skills
to develop.
Let's try the port.
I'm not sure if they're there,
but we'll give it a shot.
They usually stay
under that bridge,
the one who are new here.
It has rained
the last couple of days,
and the water has risen,
so we can't see them.
There is someone there,
but it looks like
a man with his boat.
That's his house. All he has.
There's an imaginary door
to enter his house.
These kids tell you
about themselves, their stories,
how they got here,
why they came.
It's important to know why
because there's always a story.
None want to become
18 in the centres of Ceuta and Melilla,
and they run away
by boat or in a truck
to take them to the peninsula.
They prefer risking their lives
before living in a youth centre
where violence is common
and life stands still.
Some of them,
not to say everyone,
take advantage over the new guys.
If they arrive with clothes,
money, they can...
They can and they will
take it away from them.
It's like the jungle in there.
The strong against the weak.
Days and weeks go by
and you see that
nothing has changed:
same routine, the same circle
over and over again.
Your life is meaningless
and nothing changes,
so you have to look for
an opportunity,
the dream I had
since I was a boy.
On the 26 of January, 2014,
a date I'll never forget,
I went with a friend,
at around 7 or 8 am
to jump the port's fence.
We took advantage
of the rain,
when police were letting
all the trucks go by.
We sneaked in to
a container in a truck.
The policeman verifying
everything said it was OK
and closed the container.
I had a mixed feeling
of happiness and fear.
Fear that we rightfully had
as the container was of iron
and steel, with no way
to get out.
The air conditioning was on,
but for the 45 minutes
between Ceuta and Algeciras
we were very cold.
When we got to Algeciras,
the police let all the trucks
at customs go by, except ours.
They opened it
while we were inside.
We didn't speak Spanish
but they tried
to explain that
the container would have
been closed for 23 hours
without opening it.
We were very lucky.
It takes courage to be 18,
sleep in a shelter,
and not lose hope.
Redouane does it every morning
by attending a social
integration course in carpentry
taught by the Cultural Association
La Kalle in Madrid.
We have looked for
different accommodation options
for young immigrants
between 18 and 21 years old,
but there are more people
than there are openings.
The shelter usually hosts
homeless people,
people with addictions,
and other situations
some people go through.
They have live it for 10 months.
In their case, it's hard
to do things right, be patient,
wait for an opening,
fulfil objectives,
follow the rules,
that daily struggle.
This young man
is like any other of his age
when it comes to his start
in the professional world.
I live in a shelter,
but I don't sleep well there.
Each morning I try
my best t go to the course.
I want a good job,
as a carpenter or a mechanic,
and work all year
to earn enough money to live
and send some money
to my family.
It's not an easy goal
considering his permit,
as for everyone, is temporary
and doesn't allow him to work.
To change his status,
a company must offer
an annual contract
for a full-time job.
Not a simple thing
for nationals either.
Each night, Redouane
goes back to the shelter
counting down they days
left to renew his documentation.
The same administration
that doesn't let him work,
demands him to prove
how he makes a living
to avoid his deportation.
The system treats you
like yoghurt or a carton of milk.
When you reach legal age,
you are expired
and useless.
Someone who turns 18,
reaching legal age,
is given documentation
without a work permit,
forcing you to steal
and commit other crimes.
In Málaga, Puerta Única designed
a system that does more
than give them
a place to sleep.
They help with paperwork,
teach them Spanish,
push them
to go back to school,
provide courses
to enter the work force,
and open the doors
to the professional world.
When we talk about
the young men who come,
it's important they know
they start a migration process
high on hopes, but also
with the possible failure.
They leave their countries,
losing their relationships
with family,
making it across the border...
they know people
who don't make it across
and lose those friends too.
When they turn 18
and think life is about to start,
they find themselves
in a situation of homelessness,
in a difficult situation.
Feeling they were wrong.
The permit they're given
doesn't allow them to work
and unemployment is high,
and they don't have
a competitive profile
compared to others.
You have to take advantage
of this apartment, you know?
It's as easy to lose it
as to get it. No more games.
I don't like playing games.
Well, you know games
are always around the corner.
You have to take
this opportunity now.
It's your last chance.
Now or never.
Do you need anything
for the house?
Last time you told me
about the pans, but...
Yes, we need frying pans.
Living in a flat means
independence, freedom, calm,
and is the most wanted resource
as well as the biggest commitment
to follow the rules.
Puerta Única has 37
sports in the city,
while the local government
has another 15,
but they aren't enough.
How are the neighbours?
Have you had any problems?
No problems. We don't
have problems with anyone.
Everything is going well.
I just ask
because those who have been
here a while are fine,
but the new ones,
I need to make sure
everything is OK.
Málaga Acoge works
towards emancipation projects.
Bear in mind that the kids
have been living under care,
with strict schedules
and decisions made for them.
When they start working,
it's about managing
their own independence.
We try to help
these young men
in every step
of their emancipation,
as a guidance, without making
decisions for them.
You are old enough
to be responsible.
You're not a kid anymore
and know what to do.
It's time to...
Being responsible
in the kitchen isn't easy.
I'm a cook now.
We look at the boys'
training, to try to find
a way of exploiting that,
studying the markets
and different opportunities
in Málaga.
It's usually in services,
tourism and so on,
in companies
we collaborate with,
which are more than 200,
that help us work
with young immigrants,
and help in their
professional futures.
Today we are going
to make tortilla de patata.
Besides the paella, it's
the most common dish
in Spain.
We will need potatoes,
of course, eggs,
oil, of what kind?
extra virgin olive oil,
very good. Exactly.
Salt and onion,
which is optional.
They come here
very enthusiastic
and you can tell
they want to make a new life
with a new prospect
for their future
they probably won't have
in their own country.
You all know how to cut
and cook the ingredients?
Let's get to it!
We're here to cook.
We are here to guide them
and motivate them,
as well as tell them
they have a bright future
that will depend on
their will to work.
Curl your fingers inwards.
Slowly, slowly.
I don't want it fast,
just good technique.
You'll get faster in time.
I want to learn to cook.
I think I'm good
and, if I'm lucky,
I can find a job.
That will, God willing,
help me get a start,
but it's not easy.
A job can open many doors
because it helps you
meet different people
and learn many things
about life.
It requires patience,
and patience is
the mother of science.
It's very important.
We will mix this
with the potato
and then season it
in the mix to then fry it.
I give them more to do
as I see their progress,
to simulate a situation
as close and similar
to what they can experience
in a real professional kitchen.
There's a misconception about this.
Many think we are just
a pit stop.
Many do go on
to live in Madrid,
or Bilbao and Catalonia,
it's true.
But, the percentage
that leaves is 20%.
If we do the math,
considering real numbers,
to this day
two hundred leave
and eight hundred stay.
They will still be immigrants.
The programme for young adults
of the government of Andalusia
provides these young men
with apartments
and other sources
of so-called "partial degree"
to help these boys
prepare for adulthood
while they are still
under the protection system.
I was studying,
but I didn't like school
in my country, Morocco,
so, I decided to come here.
I went to the harbour,
spent five months
on the streets,
until I hid under a truck
that brought me to Spain.
When I got here,
the police found me
and put me in
a youth centre.
Hamid is in a professional course
for construction and production.
He is one of the 1,300 users
of the Labora programme,
half of which are
young immigrants.
When they come to us,
we work on all their skills:
their personal and social skills,
as well their professional ones,
to help them develop
an independent future.
Things like professional
training, social skills,
how to open a bank account,
how a leasing contract
of a flat works, or even
how to deal
with a job interview.
Ideally, they would come
as soon as they are 16,
to give us two years
to be there for support
before they reach
the legal age in Spain.
I would like to live in Seville
and work in something
I love to do,
like electromechanics.
I want to help my family,
as they got me here,
and do it for myself.
I want to get far in life
and be able to travel.
I'll travel around the world.
The work we do
in the Labora programme
for a local kid is different
than for an immigrant.
A Spanish kid is difficult
to teach the dynamics
of being independent,
earning their own money,
while one of these boys
already has that sense of life
and wants to start working
as soon as they can.
At the end of the year,
only seven of every ten young
immigrants looking for work
is able to sign a contract.
The problem comes
for those who don't have resources
and leave the system at 18,
without professional training,
without a school diploma and,
sometimes, without the language.
They have a clear goal,
which is to work.
When they get here,
they learn that work
is attached to training,
which is key.
Getting a high school diploma
means being an individual,
which is the lowest degree
in society, as we know it.
They need it more
than their classmates
because they are in
a lower social situation,
which is unquestionable.
We mentioned the pharynx
and the oesophagus.
Where is the oesophagus?
He pulled his zipper down.
It's a tube.
-Where does the tube go?
-To the stomach.
Some of them
sleep in a car
and others sleep on a sofa
an NGO can lend them,
as there aren't enough
resources for everyone.
Keeping calm
and being constant,
to come to class
every day is not easy.
It's very difficult
and requires work.
Málaga Acoge aims
to provide high school degrees
for those who chose
to stay in Spain.
Of the 18 immigrants
studying in this
school of Vicente Espinel,
only a third of them
will go on to finish school.
Food is broken down
with our teeth.
The tongue and saliva...
Do you know what
broken down means?
-How is it in your language?
-"Broken down" in arab?
-In arab?
-Yes, how do you say it in arab?
-You won't understand.
-I know I won't.
The issue is for them
to understand
the importance of studies.
We must support them,
be on top of them,
sometimes act
as if we were
the students' parents,
or tell them off,
make them cry, hug them...
Only then will
the problem be solved.
Right now,
I'm studying in school.
I have learnt a lot
from being in school.
My teacher, Yolanda,
is a really nice person.
She is great, really incredible.
I'll get my school degree
and after I do,
I'll look for a job.
It helps to have a diploma,
and easier. Much better.
I'll find a good job
and earn money
to buy a house and a car,
have my own family
and kids. Who knows?
Sometimes I cry when
I think about my family.
They are far away
and I feel very, very sad.
They tell me to keep going
and to not look back,
to stay away from
the bad ways of life.
If you get into drugs,
your future is gone
and you'll find
yourself on the streets.
You have to walk
firmly in life.
There are many ways
to come to Spain.
For example, you can
arrive with papers in order,
but you have to pay for it.
I don't have money
to pay 3,000 euro.
Another way to come
is by crossing the border,
for which you pay
at least 500 euro,
or you can come in
through Melilla or Ceuta.
I was in the street in Melilla.
Living on the street
means being cold,
being hungry and
going through other things
that is not easy
for everyone.
When he turned 18,
Abdesalam had made
the firm decision
to get it together and study.
Upon leaving the protection
system, he left for Málaga.
Puerta Única offered him
a cooking class that changed his life.
-We have an order for a salad.
-Coming up.
I did a course to be
assistant cook
for three months with
Málaga Acoge. It was great.
I then did my internship here,
where they have hired me
and where I work.
I'm learning little by little
and have been here seven months.
All my colleagues,
the waiters,
maintenance staff, cooks,
are all really nice.
Thanks to the Incorpora programme,
financed by the La Caixa foundation,
as well as the businesses
that support these young men,
the fear caused by illegality
and exclusion fades away.
He now has the
annual contract he needed
to get his work permit.
I never used to like it,
but since I'm here,
I like cooking.
There are more jobs
as cooks in Spain.
Our experience has shown
that most young men
who enjoy resources and our time
can be independent
and live autonomously.
They go on to be
independent, have jobs,
pay their social security
and their taxes, rent,
and lead completely
normal lives,
like any other citizen.
My name is Lamin Keita.
I'm from Guinea Conakry
and I'm 17 years old.
I had always worked with my father
back in my country.
My relies a lot on me
because I helped him a lot.
I wanted to study.
Really wanted to study,
but my father...
he insisted a lot,
so I couldn't do anything.
Africa and Europe are different.
Very different. In Africa
you can't make your own
decisions without your father.
Lamin left a life
he no longer wanted
and, at 15, went on
one of the most dangerous
migratory journeys.
This path takes West Africans
through Bamako,
the capital of Mali, to the sea
and across the Saharan desert.
They asked for money,
saying they would take me
to Algeria, to the its capital.
I agreed and said OK
because I didn't know.
I didn't know if
they wanted to trick me.
We spent three days on a bus,
until we got to a city
of Mali called Gao that's at war.
They told us
we had to pay more money
and give them money
to get on a truck
that would take us there. A big truck
with more than 200 people or so.
Gao is the doorstep to the desert.
There, human traffickers
have the absolute power
before entering the land
of endless sand dunes.
They called the truck driver
because they know we have money.
They told me that
I had to pay to go through.
I was very young.
The youngest one there.
I had to pay money,
but I said I didn't have any.
I was crying and they left me.
It was a two-week trip
in the truck with nothing.
There's no food in the desert
and nowhere to buy food.
Lamin's trip is long,
stopping in different towns.
He worked, paid the mafias,
and continued his journey
making his way north.
I will not go back empty handed
without being able to help my mom.
I would rather die
than return with shame to my country.
Lamin is 17 now and should be
in a protection centre,
but lives in a flat for adults
provided by Pueblos Unidos.
Despite his documentation
stating he is a minor,
Spanish administration
considers Lamin an adult.
Two weeks
into his arrival to this
protection shelter in Madrid,
he did test to determine his age,
concluding he was more
than 18 years old,
making the judge sign off
a decree for his legal age.
I cried and didn't say anything.
My lawyer said, "Lamin,
do you want to do the test?"
He said I had to do
a full physical test.
I told him I would.
The judge also asked
"Do you want to do the test?"
I said I preferred doing it.
If my documentation don't come,
I preferred doing the test.
I did the test and they said
I was 18 years old
and that I had to leave.
The Raíces Foundation
claims such age exams
are done systematically
to children
from Sub-Saharan Africa,
Morocco, or Algeria.
It usually includes
an x-ray of the wrist,
of the mouth
and a full physical.
They take all my clothes off
and the woman was looking.
In our religion,
this is not good.
It is not allowed
for a woman to stand
and look at a naked man,
staring like that.
They did it to me
and I accepted it.
In some regions,
like Andalusia, tests
are limited to
x-rays of the wrist.
The margin of error
to determine
their age increases.
It is a test with
a high margin of error,
with a two-year variation.
Therefore, we must apply
the margin of error.
That is, if a doctor
or a radiologist
determines he is 19,
two years up or down,
the range is interpreted
to favour the minor
and establish
he is 17 years old.
In theory, the exam
must only be done
when the minor's age
and physical appearance
are clearly contradictory
and when the court,
the only authority
that can decree
if the person is a minor or not,
believes he is undocumented.
We want those
considered minors
to be in fact minors
and not adults
who try
to come in as a minor,
using as only proof
any documentation
that, in most cases,
can have errors.
In 2018, the Committee for
the Rights of the Child
was particularly
strict on Spain,
claiming the use of
invasive test to determine age,
despite being documented,
and the high exposure of risk
in the case of an error.
What does this mean?
The child is left on the streets,
with a decree that says
he is of legal age
and a passport that says
he is still a minor.
A valid passport, at that,
used by the other
Spanish administrations.
So, they can't apply
for a work permit
without a residence permit,
nor apply for
a residence permit
since they don't have
legal guardianship.
With that, they can't apply.
They can't get medical care,
they can't register, they can't
get a medical service card...
Strangely enough, that little
boy or girl, holding a passport
that says they are a minor,
can't even be deported.
They are doomed to live
in Spain in the street
until they turn 18,
according to their passport,
the same passport the judged
ruled to be invalid.
Lamin works four months in Algiers
to pay for the last part of his trip.
The goal is to reach Castillejos,
a Moroccan city
where those who can't pay
to cross the border by sea
get ready to jump
the fence in Ceuta.
There was a lot of people.
Almost 700 or so.
We tried to get in.
I was at the front.
They won't hit
the children,
so the young ones
are always at the front
to climb the fence.
We opened the door
with a hammer,
while others are jumping
over the fence.
Others tried to break
the door and the locks.
No one wants to go back.
Everyone was determined
to get across the get.
There was no other option.
We opened the first door,
reached the second one
and crossed running.
I was at the front in the video.
Some people cried
because they
had suffered a lot.
I left my country sure
that I wouldn't come back
without...
without having a new life.